Good morning. Today's דף daf is נ"ט. Nun-tet. We pick up on
the bottom of נ"ח עמוד ב' Nun-chet amud bet and we are
middle of נ"ח עמוד ב' Nun-chet amud bet and we are where
it says גידו בר רילי. Gido bar Re'ili. About six lines before
the lines get wide. We're dealing with this whole issue of סיקריקון
sikrikon
and
when it sees the property is seized because your life is being
threatened, whether it
whether
it's considered that the סיקריקון sikrikon now owns it after twelve months
that the owners didn't buy it back. That was the second level
of תקנה. takana. The first level of תקנה takana was you had
to buy it both from the סיקריקון sikrikon and the original owner
and in the right order so the original owner would not feel
compelled. Okay. So גידו בר רילי קביל ארעא בטסקא מבני באגי. Gido
bar Re'ili kavil ara betaska mibnei vaga. So גידו בר רילי Gido
bar Re'ili took the land by paying the head tax or whatever
the some type of a land tax from the people of the
valley, which basically the story was was that you owned the land,
the fields were divided, and you paid the a certain the land
tax and you kept the produce. It was your land. But apparently
the owners had had abandoned their property. And who knows where they
were. They were vacationing somewhere in Hawaii. And the and the but
the entire community was responsible for the tax of that valley. So
you you know it wasn't just the owner's bad luck. They had
to find somebody that was going to pay the tax. So what
they did was they got this גידו בר רילי Gido bar Re'ili
guy and they said listen buddy here's what we're going to do.
You work the land in the absence of the owners. You can
keep the produce and you just pay their tax. Okay, great. So
he gets a so good deal for him, good deal for everybody.
That's what they did. All right.
Now אקדים ויהיב זוזי דתלת שנין. akdim veyahiv zuzei detlat shanin. He
got a little overeager and he prepaid the tax for three years.
All right. And he hoping that he would work the land for
three years and keep all the produce. ולסוף אתו מרי דהוה קמאי.
vesof ata marei dehava kamaei. But then of course what happened was
after the first year, the original owners returned and they wanted their
land back. Okay. And it was their land, so what's he going
to say? Well, I already paid the government the tax, I'm entitled
to work on to use your land. It's my land. Okay, very
nice that you paid the whatever. So the owners said the most
reasonable thing. אמרי ליה, amrei lei, they said to him, listen, שתא
קמייתא דיהבת אכלת. shata kamaei d'yehavit achalt. The first year you paid
the tax and you ate the produce. We weren't around. But השתא
hastah from this point on it's our land אנן יהבינן ואנן אכלינן.
anan yavnan va'anan achlinan. We're now going to resume paying the tax
to the government and we're going to take the produce. Very reasonable
thing, it is their land. אתו לקמיה דרב פפא. atu lekamei deRav
Pappa.
So they came to רב פפא. Rav Pappa. סבר למכתב ליה טרפא
אבני באגי. savar lemichtav lei turfa abnei bagei.
So רב פפא Rav Pappa thought that what he would that what
he would do would be that he would write a like a
טרפא, turfa, טרפא turfa is like a deed that allows him to
collect like a writ of בית דין beis din that allows him
to collect to recoup his taxes from the people of
the of the valley. Hold on let me just check רש"י Rashi
about this one minute. Make sure I'm getting this right.
Right. Okay, yeah. So he basically, so he basically said look this
guy's entitled to get his taxes back. You appointed him, you basically
were the ones that asked him to do this. Of course as
we're going to see nobody asked him to pay three years in
advance. Okay, but now so now he's out the advance tax money
he paid. He should be able to collect from you guys.
אמר ליה רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע לרב פפא, amar lei Rav
Huna brei deRav Yehoshua leRav Pappa, so רב הונא Rav Huna said
to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, אם כן עשית סיקריקון. im ken asita
sikrikon. You've made it into a case of a סיקריקון. sikrikon. Now
why is that a case of a סיקריקון? sikrikon? Because רש"י Rashi
says that let me
let me just check רש"י Rashi again hold on.
Yeah, so it's a little hard to understand the exact analogy, but
the way רש"י Rashi is explaining it is that the same way
in the case of the סיקריקון, sikrikon, what happens is somebody sees
the land, the סיקריקון sikrikon sees the land, by the second צד
tzed of the סיקריקון sikrikon where you only reimburse the owners for
like you know for a quarter because you got a discount of
a quarter, but you basically buy it from the סיקריקון sikrikon and
even though the original land belonged to the owners, you don't you're
not going to lose as a result that it belonged to the
owners, and you get to keep the land. Okay, so they were
sort of saying well you made this something similar. The owners left,
you made it like the people of this valley were had were
taking possession of the land like they had somehow a right to
give it to this guy and this guy now that the original
owners returned doesn't isn't going to have to lose out anything, and
you're going to have to make him whole. Okay, so you're sort
of trying to make it something like this case of the סיקריקון
sikrikon in the sense that this guy paid for the right for
the land. It wasn't really his land, but we're not gonna make
him lose out. And that's sort of like the סיקריקון, sikrikon, you
bought the land from the סיקריקון sikrikon and we're not gonna make
you lose out. But of course this isn't the case of a
סיקריקון sikrikon because first
because nobody seized the land, took possession of it, threatening somebody's life.
It isn't that scenario at all. So you know, so therefore if
this guy, so so there's no fundamental assumption that he had a
right to buy the land and if the owners show up he's
not gonna lose out. There's none of that basic assumption. Okay, אלא
אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע, Ella amar Rav Huna brei d'Rav
Yehoshua, הניח מעותיו על קרן הצבי. heniah maotav al keren hatzvi. It's
like you put your money on the on the head of a
deer, meaning it's like you threw, we would say you flush your
money down the toilet. Nobody asked you to prepay for three years.
Okay? And you have no fundamental right just because the owners abandoned
the land that there is no fundamental presumption oh well and now
I'm buying it from the בני באגי benei bagi and I'm I'm
I'm I'm
ensured that I will not lose out in the deal. So it's
not at all like the סיקריקון. sikrikon. Okay, nobody was seizing the
land. It was just dealing with the fact that they had to
get their taxes paid. And too bad that you prepaid and you
flushed that money down the toilet. Yes?
When this owner comes back, is he going to have to pay
those taxes?
Yes.
So the government is going to,
what can't he just say to the guy say look you paid
it for me?
Right. Right. So that's a good question. Meaning if he since those
taxes were already prepaid, right, why can't the owner just since he's
now saved that money prepay this guy? So רש"י Rashi makes it
sound like, and I don't really understand this, רש"י Rashi makes it
sound like now that the owner is back he's going to have
to pay the taxes to the government as well. Like the government's
going to double collect. Okay. Though so that's why רש"י Rashi makes
it sound, but the idea of הניח מעותיו על קרן הצבי heniah
maotav al keren hatzvi sometimes can even mean that like okay you
did me that favor but that doesn't entitle me, you know, thank
you very much for for paying off my taxes, like that doesn't
obligate me to to, you know, pay for you. If you went
ahead and you walked into the IRS office and you said I
know Dov Linzer is behind on his taxes, let me write out
a check and you gave it to them, right, is it so
clear that now you can sue me back for that money? You
know, you did it, and nobody asked you to do it. It
might be the appropriate thing, but you know, but the גמרא's Gemara
trying to talk about like what the legal obligation is. But הניח
מעותיו על קרן הצבי heniah maotav al keren hatzvi sometimes is used
even in those types of cases where there might be some moral
responsibility but the גמרא's Gemara saying but okay but legally you're not
bound. All right. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. זו משנה ראשונה.
Zu mishna rishona. So that was an interesting case. It was a
little strange because it was not clear what the analogy was, but
that was essentially what the גמרא Gemara was saying is there is
no analogy. So therefore he threw his money away. All right. זו
משנה ראשונה. Zu mishna rishona. בית דין של אחריהן. Beit din shel
achareihen. So the first position was you had to buy it both
from the סיקריקון sikrikon and the owner. The later stage was אמר
הלוקח מן הסיקריקון נותן לבעלים רביע. amar halokeach min hasikrikon noten labealim
revia. That basically presumably were that after a year implicitly the owner
was waiving his rights or his hope that he would ever get
it back so he was like totally מיאש. meya-esh. And if he
didn't buy it back in a year, you could buy it from
the סיקריקון sikrikon and you'd only have to pay the owners a
quarter because that's how much you got it discounted. Okay. אמר רב.
Amar Rav. Now how do you figure out the quarter? So this
is going to be a little confusing. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, רביע
בקרקע או רביע במעות. revia bekarka o revia bemaot. It's either a
quarter of the land or a quarter of the money. Now it
starts, it's easier to understand it as a quarter of the money
and it's always confusing because a quarter sometimes means a fifth depending
on how you figure it. So if you basically bought a hundred
dollars, paid, paid a hundred dollars for the land, okay, a quarter
of that money is twenty-five, right? So basically which means that really
the land was worth a hundred and twenty-five and you got it
discounted twenty percent, which is twenty-five. Okay so you got a discount,
so it's, I maybe I'm already making it more confusing than necessary.
Anyway the point is you pay the owners a quarter of the
purchase price that you got it for, because that's how much you
got off from the actual original price. So if you paid a
hundred, it really was worth a hundred and twenty-five. So you pay
the owners twenty-five. Okay so that's רביע במעות. revia bemaot. You pay
them a quarter of the purchase price that you paid for. Now
רביע בקרקע revia bekarka means that or alternatively you could take this
land that you now bought and now it does not mean you
give the owners back a quarter of the land because if you
now bought this land for a hundred but it's really worth a
hundred and twenty-five, what segment of the land do you have to
give them back in order that they get twenty-five essentially twenty-five dollars'
worth of land? You bought this land, it was, you paid a
hundred but it's worth a hundred and twenty-five, so how much do
you have to give them back they get twenty-five? How much? A
fifth? Right. So רביע בקרקע revia bekarka actually means a fifth of
the land, okay? It's all very confusing. But anyway, okay. So I
understand. So anyway you give them a quarter of, this is the
way רש"י Rashi explains it, you pay them back a quarter of
the purchase price, okay, or that amount equivalent in land, which would
wind up being a fifth of the land. Okay. That's רב. Rav.
But the basic point is twenty-five dollars, a quarter of the purchase
price. ושמואל אמר רביע בקרקע שהן שליש במעות. U'Shmuel amar revia bekarka
shehen shalish bemaot. No. What you actually do is you have to
pay them a third of the purchase price, okay, 33 and a
third dollars, okay, which is because that he feels that you actually
got a bigger discount, okay, so if it was you paid 100
it's worth 133 or something. Now, if you're paying it 33 now,
if you're paying giving him back 33 dollars, okay, everybody with me
here? Okay, and so and so how and so you're giving back
a third of the purchase price, how much would that be of
the land itself? Land is worth 133, so how much of the
land do you have to give them back? If land is worth
133 and you have to give them 33 of it, how much
are you giving them back? A quarter. Okay, so that's what שמואל
Shmuel says. A quarter of the קרקא karka means literally a quarter
of the קרקא karka which is really a third of the money.
So but basically, so the קרקא karka part is a little bit
compared to confuse you, but anyway, רב Rav says it's a quarter
of the purchase price and שמואל Shmuel says it's a third of
the purchase price. Okay. במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai kamifligi? מר סבר Mar savar
גבי רביע זבין gabai revi'a zavin ונכי רביע זבין. u-nechi revi'a zavin.
One says you got a quarter discounted. ומר סבר U-mar savar meaning
so if you paid 100 it was worth 133, they knocked off
a quarter of the actual value. ומר סבר U-mar savar and the
other one holds נכי חומשא זבין. nechi chumsha zavin. You got you
got it a 20 percent discounted, okay. If you paid 100 it
was worth 125. All right. Now, מיתיבי. Meisevei. זו משנה ראשונה. Zu
mishna rishona. This is the first teaching. בית דין של אחריהם אמרו
Beis din shel achareihem amru but the second teaching said, הלוקח מן
הסיקריקון Ha-lokei'ach min ha-sikrikon if you purchase from the סיקריקון, sikrikon, נותן
לבעלים רביע nosein l'baalim revi'a you pay the owners a quarter, we're
trying to now figure out what a quarter means, ויד בעלים על
העליונה v'yad baalim al ha-elyona and the owners have the right to
choose how they want that money paid back. רצו בקרקע נוטלין Ratzu
b'karka notlin they can say give me back that equivalent in the
land that you just bought. רצו במעות נוטלין Ratzu b'maos notlin or
they can ask for it in cash. אימתי Eimasai so far this
doesn't prove anything to this debate. אימתי Eimasai when is this true?
בזמן שאין בידם ליקח B'zman she-ein b'yadam llikach if they can't buy
it back themselves. אבל יש בידם ליקח Aval yeish b'yadam llikach if
they can buy it back themselves, הן קודמין לכל אדם hein kodmin
l'chol adam they have the first right to purchase it back and
we're going to see in a minute that up till 12 months.
רבי הושיב בית דין ונמנו Rebbi hoshiv Beis Din v'nimnu Rebbi made
it sort of convened a בית דין Beis Din and they took
a vote שאם שהתה
בפני סיקריקון שנים עשר חודש
she-im shahasa bifnei sikrikon shneim
asar chodesh if it was 12 months in the hand of the
סיקריקון sikrikon after and the owner did not buy it back and
they had 12 months to buy it
back, כל הקודם ליקח זכה kol ha-kodem llikach zacha and then anybody
is free to buy it, אבל נותן לבעלים רביע בקרקע או רביע
במעות. aval nosein l'baalim revi'a b'karka o revi'a b'maos. You have to
pay the owners back a quarter of the land or a quarter
of the money. So because this ברייתא braisa ends with the phrase
a quarter of the money, we're assuming that that's evidence to רב,
Rav, that if you paid 100, you pay the owners 25. That's
evidence to רב. Rav. So אמר רב אשי Amar Rav Ashi so
how are we going to make it work with שמואל? Shmuel? כי
תניא ההיא לאחר שבאו מעות לידו. Ki tanya ha-hi l'achar she-ba'u maos
l'yado. No, no, no. A quarter of the money means that if
it was according to שמואל, Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel said I pay the
owners 33, right? So after I've paid the owners 33, how much
now have the owners got of the total money that I expended?
I paid the סיקריקון sikrikon 100. I paid the owners 33. What
percent does the owners have of the total amount that I spent
out of pocket? Out of pocket I spent 133, right? The owners
got 33, that's a quarter. So you could refer to it as
a quarter of the money for works for שמואל. Shmuel. For רב
Rav it's a quarter of the purchase price, 25. For שמואל Shmuel
it's a quarter of the total amount of money you're going to
spend out of pocket, but between both the סיקריקון sikrikon and the
owners. Okay, so you give the סיקריקון sikrikon 100, the owners 33,
you've given the owners a quarter of the money that you spent
out of pocket. Fine. I'm sure we all found that very stimulating.
Let's move on. אמר רב Amar Rav so now said רב Rav
a little bit of a
digression, אנא הוה במימניא דבי רבי. Ana hava b'minyana d'vei Rebbi. You
know what? This is quite fascinating because you know we often say
רב תנא הוא ופליג. Rav tanna hu u-palig. רב Rav was this
transitional figure between the תנאים Tannaim and the אמוראים. Amoraim. So now
we're going to have a little bit of a report that רב
Rav says, you know, it says Rebbi convened a בית דין Beis
Din and they took a vote. So Rebbi was the end of
the tannaitic period. So רב Rav says, I was in that בית
דין Beis Din that Rebbi convened when we took the vote about
the סיקריקון. sikrikon. Okay, so there you go. ומינאי דידי מנו ברישא
U-minai didi manu b'reisha and they asked for my vote first. I
was the first one to vote on that issue of the סיקריקון.
sikrikon. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara now now kind of totally digress
and talk about, oh, that's an interesting way of running a of
having a vote. והנן תנן V'hanan tnan don't we teach in a
משנה, mishna, דיני ממונות והטהרות והטומאות מתחילין מן הגדול. dinei mamonot v'ha-taharot
v'ha-tumos matchilin min ha-gadol. When a בית דין Beis Din takes a
vote, if it's monetary matters or טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, you know,
sort of ritual matters in general, so you have the you have
the oldest person give their vote first, you know, the senior person
give their vote first, because that is a shrine of respect. And
also as we're going to see, you know, people might be a
little bit hesitant to to disagree when the senior person says their
opinion, but they're entitled to disagree, okay? So that's how you run
it if it's a normal case.
But דיני נפשות, dinei nefashot, if it's a case of a capital
crime, מתחילין מן הצד. matchilin min ha-tzad. Then you have a somebody
who's not the senior person, you start from the side, not from
the... bed. Begin because you want people, number one, to feel much
freer to voice their opinions, right? Somebody's life is at stake, and
if the senior authority speaks first, everybody else is going to just,
you know, go along, be yes men, okay? So number one is
you want to make sure you want to structure it so that
everybody feels comfortable voicing their opinion. Also, as רש"י Rashi says, there's
a דרשה drasha from the פסוק pasuk לא תענה על ריב, lo
sa'aneh al riv, do not sort of like respond to a fight,
with the דרשה drasha is לא תענה על רב, lo sa'aneh al
rav, that you're not allowed to challenge a senior authority when they
give their opinion about a court case, but that's only read in
cases of דיני נפשות. dinei nefashos. Okay, so in a דיני נפשות
dinei nefashos case, a, in general if a senior authority speaks first,
you're lax to disagree, and b, you actually not allowed to disagree.
So in דיני נפשות dinei nefashos cases we have to start from
the side, from a minor person, whereas דיני ממונות, dinei mammonos, anything
else, we can start from the senior person. So the question is,
this wasn't דיני נפשות. dinei nefashos. Since it wasn't דיני נפשות, dinei
nefashos, how did רב Rav start the vote? רבי Rebbi should have
started the vote. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אמר רבה בריה
דרבה ואי תימא רב הילל בריה דרב ולס, amar Rabbah brei deRabbah
v'isayma Rav Hillel brei deRav Vallas, interesting word, name ולס, Vallas,
שאני מניינא דבי רבי. shani minyana debei Rebbi. No, no, רבי's Rebbi
court was different. דכולי מנינו ליה מן הצד. dekulei maminu lei min
hatzad. Even in all cases they started, they started with a minor,
you know, not with the head. רבי Rebbi did not start the
vote. And תוספות Tosafot explains basically because the other גמרא Gemara as
we know, like the end of סוטה, Sotah, everybody remembers what the
last משנה Mishna in סוטה Sotah says? When רבי Rebbi died,
בטל ענוה, batal anavah, right? So רבי Rebbi was humble, so humble
that even in cases in which he was entitled to give the
first vote, he chose to not. He chose to did to be
free diff, you know, free debate, free discussion, let the other people
start the vote and he voted at the end. Okay? So that's
how רב Rav could have voted first even though it was a
case that רבי Rebbi should have voted first, you know, the head
should have voted first, רבי Rebbi allowed other people, you know, רבי
Rebbi was מוחל mochal on that, which in the end is better
anyway, it allows for freer discussion.
Okay,
now because we made that comment about רבי Rebbi or that implicit
comment about his ענוה anavah and we talked about him convening a
בית דין, beis din, now the גמרא Gemara is going to continue
in that vein.
מן הצד הוו מתחילין. min hatzad havu matchilin. ואמר רבה בריה דרבה
ואי תימא רב הילל בריה דרב ולס, v'amar Rabbah brei deRabbah v'isayma
Rav Hillel brei deRav Vallas, so now another statement about from these,
from this, from this tradition, from, you know, this אמורא, Amora, מימות
משה ועד רבי, mi-yemos Moshe v'ad Rebbi, from the time of משה
רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu until רבי, Rebbi, לא מצינו תורה וגדולה במקום אחד.
lo matzinu Torah u'gedulah bemakom echad. We've never had a case where
in one generation, all the greatest תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and the
greatest, you know, גדולה gedola authority, as רש"י Rashi says it means
wealth, but one might say sort of societal status, you know, were
in one person, were combined in one person, you know? And obviously
you've had people that were great תלמידי חכמים, talmidei chachamim, we've had
people of great wealth and of great status, but that it would
be the same person that would be both, that we've never had
since משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. Of course, it's an interesting question because,
you know, other things make it sound like רבי Rebbi was not
necessarily the biggest תלמיד חכם talmid chacham of his time, but so
does it mean he was the best of both of them or
was that degree of stature combined with that degree of תורה Torah
knowledge, you know, never occurred all in one person until from the
time of משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu until now? Yes.
This would seem to violate the basic principle of ירידת הדורות. yeridas
hadoros.
Well, no, because it's all relative. Meaning, you know, in any generation
that one person should have both of those together, right? Anyway, so
okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ולא, v'lo, is that really true?
That this, that it was not from then until now? הוי יהושע.
havei Yehoshua. So how about in the time of יהושע? Yehoshua? He
was the king and he was presumably משה's Moshe student, so he
was the biggest תלמיד חכם talmid chacham as well. So the גמרא
Gemara says no, הוי אלעזר. havei Elazar. No, there was אלעזר Elazar
there, who also, you know, was אהרן's Aharon student, big תלמיד חכם,
talmid chacham, he had a lot of authority. Now one could ask
this question because I mean, still the authority of the king is
a little bit greater than the authority of the כהן גדול, kohen
gadol, but I don't know, maybe one is a religious authority and
one is a political authority. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says at
least anyway, he had a real competitor there for that title. So
the גמרא Gemara says הוי אלעזר. havei Elazar. So fine, when יהושע
Yehoshua died, אלעזר, Elazar, he was the only guy in town. He
was the—he had both of those combined. It says no, הוי פנחס.
havei Pinchas. There was פנחס Pinchas that was still alive. So who
also presumably was a big תלמיד חכם talmid chacham and a lot
of authority. Again, he wasn't the כהן גדול kohen gadol though, you
know. So again one wonders exactly what, like, you know, like it's
basically saying there was nobody comparable, not exactly nobody, nobody exactly equal,
because, you know, פנחס Pinchas and אלעזר Elazar were both כהנים, kohanim,
they weren't even one—one wasn't one political, one religious, and אלעזר Elazar
was the כהן גדול. kohen gadol. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara says הוי
פנחס, havei Pinchas, so what?
Maybe it's about the relative, about the relative stature and the relative
learning.
The combination of the two.
Yeah, like יהושע, Yehoshua, sure, he was in charge, but he was—and
he was a big תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, but פנחס Pinchas was
also a big תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, so יהושע Yehoshua wasn't that
much ahead of...
right, right, so it wasn't a huge gap. Right, they were in
the same ballpark.
רבי Rebbi was the acknowledged leader. and he was a
far...
He was a far greater תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. Right, so it
doesn't seem like there was nobody in the ballpark. It seems to
say. It's not like an exact question, no, you get a ninety-eight
and you get a ninety-six, you know? There was nobody in the
ballpark. So the גמרא Gemara says והא פנחס? V'ha Pinchas? How about
when אלעזר Elazar died, פנחס Pinchas was the man? No, הוה זקנים.
Havah Zekenim. No, there were the elders. Now, of course, and they
also had some political authority as well and they were understood as,
you know, in the line of tradition from משה Moshe to יהושע,
Yehoshua, yes.
But it says repeatedly in ספר שופטים, Sefer Shoftim, אין מלך בישראל,
Ein melech b'Yisrael, yeah, and that everyone was doing their thing. There
wasn't really much...
No, but there were... I mean there were שופטים, shoftim, there were
political authorities, but you're right.
And פנחס Pinchas certainly is never described as a שופט. shofet.
Right, right. Well, we're not saying necessarily political authority, it might be
religious authority. So the גמרא Gemara says, okay. So the גמרא Gemara
says והא שאול? V'ha Shaul? He was a king and according to
rabbinic tradition he also was a big תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham. No,
הוה שמואל, Havah Shmuel, who again wasn't a king but he had
was like the head religious authority. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
והא נח נפשיה? V'ha nach nafshai? When שמואל Shmuel died while שאול
Shaul was still alive, so שאול Shaul at least at that stage
was the only guy in town. גמרא Gemara says כולי שני קאמינא.
Kulei shani ka'amina. We mean somebody that his entire life he was,
or entire let's say professional life, you know, he was the only
person, he was never contested, there's no equivalent. גמרא Gemara says והא
דוד? V'ha David? How about דוד, David, king and a big תלמיד
חכם talmid chacham as anybody who learns ברכות Brachos knows that. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, no, הוה עירא היאירי, Havah Ira haYairi,
but you never even heard of עירא היאירי. Ira haYairi. Okay, anyway,
but according to rabbinic tradition he was like a huge תלמיד חכם.
talmid chacham. Now the funny thing about this is he might have
been a huge תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, but he certainly wasn't anybody
who had any authority, right? Until now we've been going with people
that had both. So is that enough that you're not entitled to
this mantle if, you know, somebody else is equivalent to you in
one of those areas? So it seems like the response is getting
to be a little weaker. Okay,
right. רש״י Rashi just says גדול בתורה. Gadol baTorah. He doesn't address
the other sense of the גדולה. gedula. והא נח נפשיה? V'ha nach
nafshai?
So one minute, this guy died while דוד David was alive, עירא
היאירי. Ira haYairi. So גמרא Gemara says, no, כולי שני קאמינא. Kulei
shani ka'amina. Nope.
So דוד David wasn't the only guy of that authority his entire
career. והא שלמה? V'ha Shlomo? הוה שלמה. Havah Shlomo.
So he was, you know, big
תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, nobody was as wise as him in the
land and he was king. הוה שמעי בן גרא, Havah Shimi ben
Gera, who again was seen as a big תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham,
again not with the same authority. So one wonders what the exact
response is. Anyway, והא קטליה. V'ha katlei. Ah, but שמואל Shmuel dealt
with that problem. I mean שלמה, Shlomo, he killed him. He killed
שמעי בן גרא. Shimi ben Gera. Ah, כולי שני קאמינא. Kulei shani
ka'amina. Ah, but he wasn't uncontested his entire career.
I understand. והא חזקיהו? V'ha Chizkiyahu? How about King חזקיהו? Chizkiyahu? So
which also we assume he was a big תלמיד חכם. talmid chacham.
הוה שבנא, Havah Shevna,
who was also seen as a sage. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, הא איקטל. Ha iktal. שבנא Shevna was killed. No, כולי
שני קאמינא. Kulei shani ka'amina. But okay, but חזקיהו Chizkiyahu wasn't told
this status, didn't hold this status his entire career.
Why שבנא Shevna not ישעיהו? Yeshayahu?
I have no idea. והא עזרא? V'ha Ezra? הוה עזרא, Havah Ezra,
right? עזרא הסופר, Ezra HaSofer, right? Political leader, religious leader, huge תלמיד
חכם. talmid chacham.
הוה נחמיה בן חלקיה. Havah Nechemya ben Chilkiya. All right, so we
now have answered all the problems. אמר ברייתא דבי רבי, Amar baraita
d'vei Rebbi, אף אני
אומר Af ani omer also similarly, מימות רבי ועד רב אשי Miyamos
Rebbi v'ad Rav Ashi לא מצינו תורה וגדולה במקום אחד. lo matzinu
Torah ugedula bimkom echad.
We haven't had that. So now רב אשי Rav Ashi also, he
is apparently was a person, I, you know, we don't know this
about רב אשי, Rav Ashi, but a person of great wealth or
stature, I don't know if he had political authority. Anyway, and he
also was the biggest תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, so he also but
was like this model of combining these two that we haven't had
anybody like that from the time of רבי. Rebbi. So the גמרא
Gemara says ולא? V'lo? No? והא הוה הונא בר נתן? V'ha havah
Huna bar Nasan? Who again apparently had both of these qualities. But
says שאני הונא בר נתן דמיכף הוה כייף ליה לרב אשי. Shani
Huna bar Nasan d'mikaf havah kaif lei l'Rav Ashi. No, he actually
was not the main authority because he actually submitted himself to the
authority of רב אשי, Rav Ashi, so that is not a good
counterexample. Okay, that was an interesting end to that whole discussion. All
right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: חרש, Cheresh, back
to תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam type of things. But you're right, it's
not a ירידת הדורות Yeridas Hadoros type of a thing. It says
like, you know, things go on a hiatus, but then you have
some, you know, going back to the old times. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara says like this: חרש, Cheresh, back to תיקון עולם Tikkun
Olam types of things. But, you know, we're sort of moving a
little away and the phrase of תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam has a
little bit dropped by the wayside because we're moving to rabbinic תקנות
takkanot to address sort of problems, sometimes changing circumstances like this סיקריקון,
sikrikon, and maybe like, you know, but they're not like necessarily like
the תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam seemed to address like deep societal systemic
issues that we had to take on. These are seen as like
a little bit more like a פרוזבול, pruzbul, what were some of
the other תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam issues? I'm trying to now remember,
the עבדים, avadim, the פדיון שבויים, pidyon shvuyim, and so on. Although...
You know, this one that we're about to look at seems to
be as broad in this משנה, Mishna, does seem to be as
broad as some of those others, but nevertheless, it's interesting that the
phrase תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam a little bit drops by the wayside.
So let's take a look.
חרש רומז ונרמז. Cheresh, Romez, v'Nirmas. So חרש Cheresh is a deaf-mute.
Now, I want to say something about deaf-mute, there's not going to
be a full analysis of that, we had some of that in
יבמות, Yevamos,
but, you know, deaf-mute as you know is considered halachically to be
not a בר דעת, bar daas, to be not of a, you
know, full mind, full intellectual capacities, and as such, he cannot enter
into like legally binding transactions: buying and selling, קידושין, kiddushin, גירושין, geirushin,
like any type of thing, you know, has מצוות, mitzvot, he can't
blow שופר shofar for somebody, he's not, you know, חייב במצוות, chayav
b'mitzvot, he's not a בר דעת bar daas like a minor. Now,
that being said, there is an opinion in the גמרא Gemara that
actually does consider him to be a בר דעת, bar daas, or
at least says that you would have a case-by-case inspection of him
and you would determine on a case-by-case basis how aware he was
and so on, and even those that say he's not a בר
דעת, bar daas, you know, he's in a different category than like
a שוטה. shoteh. A שוטה shoteh is somebody who's seen as like,
you know, unable to properly interpret reality, maybe like schizophrenic or something,
whereas a whereas he is considered to be like, okay, he might
be like weak in the דעת, daas, but not completely not a
בר דעת, bar daas, and that's going to allow for us to
make actually some תקנות takanot and allow him to play a certain
type of role within the society. Now, of course this is to
some degree understandable, you know, before they had education for the deaf,
and when they really felt that, you know, he wasn't able to
understand what I'm saying, I can't understand what he's saying, you know,
maybe they make weird gestures or they talk funny or whatever, so
so there was this perception like he really can't really fully understand.
Now, the other interesting thing is is that I had always assumed
like, how often do you have somebody who's both deaf and mute?
Like usually you get somebody who's deaf, but, you know,
חרש, Cheresh, deaf-mute, how often did that happen? What I don't think
I appreciated was that they were basically defining almost every deaf person
as deaf-mute, because deaf people were not able to talk in an
intelligible way. So so because, you know, they can't hear their own
talk and they can't modulate how they're talking, so so it was
really the rare חרש Cheresh who was just deaf, it was somebody
who actually had mostly had been born hearing and then lost their
hearing. So pretty much every deaf person was put into this category.
What you wind up having, and this is not for us, but
and it's not going to even really come up in the גמרא,
Gemara, but what you wind up having is in the last few
hundred years, especially when they started the schools for the deaf and
people it was very obvious that the that somebody could be deaf
and, you know, even if they couldn't talk in an intelligible way,
you know, and be quite intelligent and clearly communicate and so on,
that it led many פוסקים poskim to have a reassessment halachically about
how to define this category. Some sort of tried to sort of
finesse it by saying that if they're able to talk via sign
language, then they're not then they're not defined as mute, then they
are talking, they're just talking through sign language, so, you know, technically
they're not in the category of חרש Cheresh anymore. Anyway, but that's
important because to understand that even in the גמרא, Gemara, they were
seen as having a good, you know, a good degree of דעת,
daas, not enough דעת, daas, but a good degree. So that's why
we have the following תקנה: takkanah: חרש רומז ונרמז. Cheresh Romez v'Nirmas.
They can actually engage in buying and selling through gestures. So you
know, through their gestures, you know, they point to the object that
they want and they hold out ten dollars or whatever, through their
gestures, even though they can't fully express anything, they can engage in
transactions. And that was a rabbinic תקנה takkanah because it was assumed
that דאורייתא d'Oraita they're not בר דעת bar daas and it's not
binding. ובן בתירה אומר קופץ ונקפץ. U'Ben Beteira omer kofetz v'nikpatz. Even
if it isn't like hand gestures, even if it's just
like jumping up and down,
that also is a sufficient gesture, whereas presumably the חכמים Chachamim felt
that that was too hard to interpret. במטלטלין, B'metaltelin,
now all of this is about purchase of chattel, not of land.
Land was seen to be too weighty of a purchase that we,
you know, basically and there wasn't enough of a need to institute
this תקנה, takkanah, as we'll see, the basic need to institute the
תקנה takkanah is how are you supposed to go about your life
if nobody will sell you, you know, you can't go to the
store and buy and buy milk and eggs. I can't sell it
to you because you're a חרש, Cheresh, so, you know, it's not
going to be binding or then I'm going to get in trouble
and you're going to ask for the money back and you say
you didn't mean it or who knows what, right? So in order
to just engage in normal life, you have to be able to
do basic types of buy and sell. But קרקע, karka, that was
seen as a, not necessary and b, too weighty, that we didn't
want to that we did not make a תקנה takkanah for that.
Now, הפעוטות, ha'pe'utot, similarly פעוטות pe'utot which are young kids, מקחן מקח
וממכרן ממכר במטלטלין. mekachan mekach u'mimcharan mimchar b'metaltelin. They can buy and
sell chattel so that you can send your kid to the store
and that works at a rabbinic level even though דאורייתא d'Oraita they're
not yet an adult. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, מחלוקת במטלטלין. machlokes b'metaltelin. This is
this debate about whether jumping up and down works as or or
just hand gestures. That's about the מטלטלין mitaltelin case of our משנה.
Mishna. אבל בגיטין, Aval b'gittin, when it comes to a גט, get,
remember גיטין, Gittin, דברי הכל ברמיזה, divrei hakol b'remiza, everybody says that
you have to do a hand gesture, you can't jump up and
down. What's the case of a גט? get?
If somebody, a man married a woman while he was, let's talk
about the man, I mean it's relevant to the woman also, but
let's talk about the man. When he was hearing and then after
he was married and it was a דאורייתא de'oraita binding marriage, he
became deaf and mute. In that type of a case, there's no
way to get out of the marriage because he is a full
דאורייתא de'oraita marriage and if he's not a בר דעת bar da'at
he can't give a גט. get. Okay? But if he is a
deaf-mute when he entered into the marriage, then it was only the
same way we allowed a חרש cheresh to purchase property, to purchase
and buy and sell, we were instituted this actually interesting, you would
have expected this to be the first thing to be said in
מסכת גיטין, Masechet Gittin, but okay, we instituted a קידושין kiddushin for
a חרש. cheresh. This actually comes up in a משנה mishna in
יבמות. Yevamot. Okay, we allowed a חרש cheresh to get married or
a חרשתא cheresheta to get married and we instituted a rabbinic קידושין.
kiddushin. Okay, if they're married only as long as one party is
a חרש, cheresh, the man or the woman, it's only binding rabbinically.
If they entered, if that was their state when they got married.
Okay? So if they are, if this rabbinic קידושין kiddushin and they're
חרש cheresh and one of them is a חרש cheresh and it's
rabbinic, let's say he's the חרש, cheresh, then when it's time to
get divorced, since it was only a קידושין kiddushin rabbinically, we'll allow
them to get divorced rabbinically as well and he can signal to
the סופר, sofer, you know, he can say like this and whatever
he's doing, you know, and he signals and it's clear they want
a גט get written to give to his wife and that's okay
even though he hasn't said anything. Okay? Yeah. ר"ג. Reish Gimel.
Right, okay, anyway.
So that's the case. So when do we say that jumping up
and down might work according to בן בתירא? Ben Beteira? That's by
מטלטלין. mitaltelin. But by a גט, get, that's again in a case
of a of when the whole קידושין kiddushin was only rabbinic because
he was a חרש cheresh when he got married, so in a
case of a of that, of a גט, get, everybody requires the
more the clearer act of רמיזה. remiza. So the גמרא Gemara says
פשיטא, peshita, it's obvious, because מטלטלין תנן, mitaltelin tenan, our משנה Mishna
is talking about מטלטלין. mitaltelin. No, מהו דתימא אף במטלטלין, mahu de-teima
af b'mitaltelin, I'm going to thought the משנה Mishna meant that every
that jumping up and down maybe certainly, you know, the debate is
by the גט, get, that's also the debate by a גט, get,
but maybe by מטלטלין mitaltelin I would have said the opposite. Everybody
needs רמיזה remiza because at least by the גט get you're just
undoing a rabbinic institution, so maybe our standards would have been lower
by a גט. get. Okay, קא משמע לן kamashma lan that that's
not the way to read the משנה, Mishna, that the debate here
it's here it's by מטלטלין, mitaltelin, by a גט get the standards
are higher and everybody requires רמיזה. remiza. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some
say אמר רב נחמן, Amar Rav Nachman, כמחלוקת במטלטלין כך מחלוקת בגיטין.
k'machloket b'mitaltelin kach machloket b'gittin.
It's the same debate, בן בתירא Ben Beteira would allow the jumping
up and down. גמרא Gemara says, והנן במטלטלין תנן? v'nan b'mitaltelin tenan?
But our משנה Mishna just says מטלטלין. mitaltelin. אימא אף במטלטלין. Eima
af b'mitaltelin. No,
even in מטלטלין mitaltelin they say this debate but the debate also
holds by גט get and so that's the question. But a חרש
cheresh can get married and can give a גט get the same
way if it's a rabbinic marriage, a rabbinic גט, get, but he
has to do his רמיזה, remiza, his gesturing and בן בתירא Ben
Beteira according to the second approach would say that even there jumping
up and down works. Okay. Now הפעוטות, ha-pe'uta, we move quickly now
to the kids, the young kids, מקח וממכר במטלטלין, mekach umemkar b'mitaltelin,
they can also buy and sell like cattle. So the גמרא Gemara
says, now ועד כמה, v'ad kama, until what age meaning down, to
you know, how old do they have to be? So מחוי רב
יהודה לרב יצחק בריה machvi Rav Yehuda l'Rav Yitzchak brei כבר שית
כבר שבע. k'var sheish k'var sheva. So רב יהודה Rav Yehuda indicated
to רב יצחק בריה Rav Yitzchak brei his son like six or
seven. So like six or seven means that there's no exact amount,
like it sounds like a little case by case, like you know,
when they get to a certain level, the understanding of a six-year-old,
a seven-year-old, enough to understand the meaning of what they're doing, how
much money is and whatever, you know, you know, sometimes I send
my kids to like, you know, the bagel store, give them 20
dollars, buy a bagel, whatever, and they get the guy the rest
for a tip or something. So not exactly, I'm exaggerating a little.
But anyway, מחילה mechila for my kids for that story. But
anyway. So yes, you understand how much money is and what you
do with the change and what's the right thing and you're not
being overcharged like at that age. Okay, six or seven, whatever the
case might be.
Does מטלטלין mitaltelin mean like an indication in sign language?
Yeah, that's actually a good point. The juxtaposition here with מטלטלין mitaltelin
hearing would have made it a just well. Right, I say I
actually it didn't occur to me the juxtaposition right about gesturing and
then gesturing. That's a good point. All right, anyway. No, actually wouldn't
made a point because it wasn't a pun.
Anyway. Okay. So anyway, רב כהנא אמר Rav Kahana amar כבר שבע
כבר שמנה, k'var sheva k'var shemona, seven or eight. מתניתא תני Matnita
tani כבר תשע כבר עשר, k'var tesha k'var eser, nine or ten.
So nobody knows exactly. I mean not nobody knows, but there's all
these different
different definitions. ולא פליגי, V'lo pligi, these don't debate. כל חד וחד
לפי חורפיה. kol chad v'chad l'fi chorfei. Everyone, you know, it depends
how sharp they are. Of course, that's not very helpful because the
question isn't, okay, so there's no exact biological age, but tell me
what like level of intelligence you're looking for, right? That's not clear.
But anyway. All right, וטעמא מאי? v'ta'ama mai? Now why did they
institute this? אמר רב אבא בר יעקב אמר רבי יוחנן Amar Rav
Ava bar Yaakov Amar Rabbi Yochanan משום כדי חייו, mishum k'dei chaya,
like I told you, because the guy's got to, you know, live.
In the society. Now of course that's more of a case of
a חרש, cheresh, but even kids, they've got to, first of all,
that type of society wasn't just I got to be able to
send my kid to the
store, sometimes by the time they're six or seven, they're out of
the house. They're apprenticing themselves, you know, they do have to fend
for themselves
a
little bit. All right, okay. ויאמר לאשר על המלתחה Vayomer la'asher al
hamaltechah and he said to the one who was on the מלתחה.
maltechah. This is by Yoash I think it
is, הוצא לבוש לכל עבדי הבעל, hotzei levush lechol ovdei habaal, take
out the clothes for all those who worship the, I'm sorry, יהוא,
Yehu, take out the clothes for all those who worship the Baal.
So מלתחה, maltechah, what is this מלתחה? maltechah? The reason we're saying
it is because it's the same רב אבא בר יעקב Rav Abba
bar Yaakov in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, the same
בעל מימרא. baal memra. אמר רב אבא בר יעקב אמר רבי יוחנן,
amar Rav Abba bar Yaakov amar Rabbi Yochanan, דבר הנימלל ונמתח, davar
hanimlal venimtach, something that is like, you know, like twisted by the
hands and stretched, which means that it's like a, it's a, what
do you call it? It's a
linen garment that, you know, when you take linen, it's like, you
know, linen comes from these little balls of whatever, flax, and you
sort of spin it by the hand and it's stretched or whatever.
So there's these fancy linen garments. So that's the word מלתחה. maltechah.
כי אתא רבין אמר
רבי יוחנן, ki ata Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan, the only reason quoted
is because it was the רב אבא בר יעקב אמר רבי יוחנן.
Rav Abba bar Yaakov amar Rabbi Yochanan. כי אתא רבין אמר רבי
יוחנן, ki ata Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan, שידר ליה בוניא בן נוניא
לרבי, shidar leih Bunaya ben Nunaya le-Rabbi, so בוניא בן נוניא, Bunaya
ben Nunaya, maybe some big Roman person, sent to רבי, Rabbi, we
mentioned רבי Rabbi before, and this is going to be tied into
the flax, to the linen
garment, סיבני וחומס סלסלה ומלמלא, sivni vechumes salsala umalmala, these different types
of fancy fabric garments. So what are סיבני וחומס? sivni vechumes? So
that is כאגוזה ופלגא דאגוזה, ke'agoza ufalga de'agoza, like a nut and
a half a nut. רש"י Rashi says what it means is it
is such a fine and thin fabric that you could take a
cloak that you put on your whole body and you fold it
up and the whole size of it is just the size of
a nut. So that's how thin and fine the fabric is, or
a nut and a half,
ופלגא דאגוזה. ufalga de'agoza. סלסלה ומלמלא, salsala umalmala, which is these other
fabrics, is כפיסטקא ופלגא דפיסטקא, kepistaka ufalga depistaka, that if you folded
it up according to רש"י, Rashi, that would just be the size
of a, what's this, פיסטקא pistaka again?
Oh, a pistachio, I'm sorry. Okay, it would just be the size
of a pistachio and a half. Okay, anyway, very fancy linen garments.
מאי מלמלא? mai malmala? דבר הנימלל ונמתח, davar hanimlal venimtach, and now
we said the same type of etymology we gave before, something that
is like spun and stretched. Okay, now back to our פעוטות. pe'utos.
וטעותן עד כמה? v'ta'utan ad kamah? If these פעוטות pe'utos overpay, until
how much, you know,
when can the transaction be, you know, be voided if they're going
to make a mistake and overpay? Probably much more likely that they
would overpay than underpay, people would take advantage of them. So אמר
רבי יוחנן אמר רבי זירא, amar Rabbi Yochanan amar Rabbi Zeira, עד
שתות כגדול, ad shtus k'gadol, until a sixth like an adult, which
basically means the laws of an adult is is that if you
overpay the market rate, then up to a sixth the transaction is
good and you get the overage back, and more than a sixth
actually the transaction is void, so it follows the same rules. Okay,
בעי אביי, ba'ei Abaye, now אביי Abaye asked, מתנתו מה, matnaso mah,
can they give a gift? That's a really good question, there's less
of a reason to make that תקנה, takanah, it's not normal transactions,
maybe more opportunity for them to be taken advantage of. Can they
give a gift?
רב יימר אמר אין מתנתו מתנה, Rav Yeimar amar ein matnaso matnah,
it's not. מר בר רב אשי אמר מתנתו מתנה, Mar bar Rav
Ashi amar matnaso matnah, it is a good gift.
אפכוה ושדרוה לקמיה דרב מרדכי, apchuha veshadruha likmei d'Rav Mordechai, so when
they sent it to רב מרדכי Rav Mordechai to ask his opinion,
רש"י Rashi says this was accidentally, they accidentally reversed the opinions of
who said what. Okay, so they asked רב מרדכי, Rav Mordechai, they
said we got this debate, is it a good gift, what's your
opinion, and then they reversed who had said what. They said מר
בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi said it's no good, and
רב יימר Rav Yeimar said it is good, which is the reverse
of what they actually said. Okay, so אמר להו, amar lehu, so
when רב מרדכי Rav Mordechai was asked, he said זילו אמרו ליה
לבר מר, zilu imru leh l'bar mar, go tell the son of
my master, because his, רב אשי Rav Ashi was his master, so
מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi was his master's son.
So go tell מר בר רב אשי, Mar bar Rav Ashi, I
mean his רבי Rebbe's son, go tell מר בר רב אשי. Mar
bar Rav Ashi. Now מר בר רב אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi
really said it's good, but they reported to him that he said
it's no good. So go tell מר בר רב אשי, Mar bar
Rav Ashi, לאו הכי הוה עובדא, lav hachi hava uvda,
one minute, don't you remember the story? כי הוי קאי מר, ki
hava ka'ei mar, when the master, רב אשי, Rav Ashi, your father,
my רבי, Rebbe, was standing, חד כרעא ארעא וחד כרעא אדרגא, chad
k'ra'a ar'a vechad k'ra'a adarga, he was like walking up the steps.
רש"י Rashi says to the בית המדרש. Beis HaMedrash. He had one
leg on the ground, one leg on the step. Okay, he was
walking, he was reminding him about what the event was. Don't you
remember the story? He was there, he was walking, he was half
up the ground, half off the, you know, half on the ground,
half on the steps. ואמרינן ליה, ve'amrinan leih, and we said to
him, מתנתו מה? matnaso mah? Wait, wait, what's the story if a
פעוטות pe'utos gives a gift? Okay, and אמר לן, amar lan, and
he said to us, מתנתו מתנה, matnaso matnah, it is good, אחת
מתנת שכיב מרע, achas matnas shechiv mera, whether he gives it on
a deathbed, that's pretty... scary to think about a six-year-old on a
deathbed. אחת מתנת בריא Achas matnas bari whether he gives it as
a healthy person, אחת מתנת מרובה Achas matnas merubah whether it's big,
אחת מתנת מועטת Achas matnas muetes whether it's small, it's good, and
that of course מר בר אשי Mar bar Ashi also said that
it was good, he's just, it was just reported incorrectly. תוספות Tosafot
says that however it does not say whether מטלטלין Metaltelin or קרקע,
Karka, which makes sense, because here the question is that maybe a
gift is worse than a transaction, but all we're talking about is
in the context of מטלטלין. Metaltelin. קרקע Karka doesn't work at all
because again there was no need and it was a more much
more weighty transaction. Okay, now we switch from תיקון עולם Tikkun olam
explicit or implicit to מפני דרכי שלום. Mipnei darchei shalom. מפני דרכי
שלום Mipnei darchei shalom
is sort of more about just
to minimize fights, okay, to adopt certain types of conventions, maybe not
completely arbitrary conventions, sometimes they might be arbitrary, but in order to
just minimize sources of conflict and a fight. Like you know we
were recently learning in the ישיבה Yeshiva about life cycles and about
ברית מילה Bris milah and פדיון הבן, Pidyon haben, and everybody wants
to know, okay so like what what are the rules about who
gets the right to name the baby? Does it go after the
father's parents, the mother's parents, who gets the right? So I basically
said, look, I can't get too excited about this, it's all just
like מנהג, Minhag, there's no real הלכה Halacha about this type of
thing. But the real purpose of knowing what the מנהג Minhag is
is not that you should feel compelled to follow it, but that
it could make things less contentious if everybody knows there's a way
of doing about it. Okay, this is your turn, then it's my
turn, or whatever. So that's sometimes having certain conventions and certain מנהגים
Minhagim are just helpful that just heads off people getting into a
fights about everything. There's a way in which it's done. Okay, so
this is going to be the type of a דרכי שלום. Darchei
shalom. Let's take a look. And sometimes they'll actually be a logic
behind this. אלו דברים אמרו מפני דרכי שלום. Elu devarim amru mipnei
darchei shalom. The following things are said for the ways of peace.
כהן Kohen קורא ראשון Korei rishon ואחריו V'acharav לוי Levi ואחריו V'acharav
ישראל. Yisrael. When you get an עליה, Aliyah, כהן, Kohen, לוי, Levi,
ישראל. Yisrael. So there obviously it's following a well-established
hierarchy and that way there's not going to be regular, of course
there's still fighting for which עליה Aliyah you're going to get if
you're a
ישראל. Yisrael. Like I think I told you this story about,
I know a guy who basically he was like very very מקפיד
Makpid on his כבוד. Kavod. So like the only עליה Aliyah he
would ever expected was like either שלישי Shelishi or שישי. Shishi. שישי
Shishi is חסידיש Chasidish is considered to be like the best עליה
Aliyah anyway. So one day the גבאי Gabbai didn't know who he
was or
whatever, he gave him
חמישי, Chamishi, which is considered to be like the worst, maybe שביעי
Shevi'i is worse, I don't know anyway. So the guy whatever, he
walked up, it was like obviously a very חשיב Chashuve רב Rav
anyway, he walks up to the ספר תורה, Sefer torah, he takes
out his סידור, Siddur, he looks in it, he makes the ברכה,
Bracha, ברוך אתה ה׳, Baruch atah Hashem, he makes the ברכה. Bracha.
So the גבאי Gabbai says to him, what, you don't know the
ברכה? Bracha? He says, listen, שלישי Shelishi I know, שישי Shishi I
know, חמישי Chamishi I don't know. Anyway, so it's not like there
aren't fights over the ישראל Yisrael parts, but at least the basic
structure
resolves a lot of fights at least at the beginning de facto.
Okay, also because, and this actually is interesting when you think about
it, the difference between, you know there's something very egalitarian, and I
don't mean that about the women's issue, but I don't exclude women's
issue, about the whole חז״ל Chazal's approach to תלמוד תורה. Talmud torah.
You know, it's like הכל עולים למנין שבעה, Hakol olim l'minyan shivah,
ואפילו אשה ואפילו קטן. V'afilu ishah v'afilu katan. And a similar thing
they say where they say like what's the sense of priority of
when you save somebody, כהן Kohen before לוי Levi before ישראל, Yisrael,
but they say that's when they're all equal. But if you have
a תלמיד חכם Talmid chacham ממזר Mamzer comes before כהן גדול עם
הארץ. Kohen gadol am ha'aretz. So תורה Torah is the big equalizer.
It's the exact, it's sort of like going back to the גמרא
Gemara we read about רבן יוחנן בן זכאי Rabban Yochanan ben Zakkai
about rabbinic judaism supplanting temple judaism. Temple judaism is all about hierarchy,
תורה Torah is all about right
equal access, the big equalizer and so on. תורה בקרן זוית מונח
כל הרוצה לבוא ויטול, Torah bekeren zavis munach kol harotzeh lavo v'yitol,
as opposed to כתר כהונה Keter kehunah and כתר מלכות, Keter malchus,
that's the big equalizer. So here you have this institution of קריאת
התורה Krias hatorah and the real הלכה Halacha is that the biggest
תלמיד חכם Talmid chacham should get the first עליה. Aliyah. It's to
all be about access to the תורה Torah and everybody, that's why
in
principle אפילו אשה Afilu ishah etc., and that's why ממזר תלמיד חכם
קודם לכהן גדול עם הארץ. Mamzer talmid chacham kodem l'kohen gadol am
ha'aretz. But of course the problem with that is that then you're
always going to get into a fight because I'm the bigger תלמיד
חכם, Talmid chacham, I'm the bigger תלמיד חכם. Talmid chacham. So on
the one hand it's the big equalizer, but you don't know because
you don't have that sort of well-defined
hierarchy predefined just by status as opposed to somebody's accomplishment.
So that's the flipside of that sort of egalitarian thing is you
don't know anybody's preassigned role. Okay, so that's here, they sort of
reinstituted this hierarchy even in the context of קריאת התורה Krias hatorah
מפני דרכי שלום. Mipnei darchei shalom. Oh
yeah, that's a good point too, right. And who is the greatest
and who achieves that greatness? Yes, right. So it allows everybody equal
access, but then we could always be fighting about who's in which
position as opposed to a well-established hierarchy which makes it very clear
who's in what position. Okay? So okay, מפני דרכי שלום. Mipnei Darkhei
Shalom. מערבין בבית ישן מפני דרכי שלום. Arvin bevayis yashan mipnei darkhei
shalom. When you have an עירוב eiruv in a תחום, tchum, or
you know, excuse me, not an עירוב תחומין, eiruv tchumim, an עירוב
חצרות, eiruv chatzeros, you have all these courtyards or houses that get
together and they put all the, you know, and they have like
a box of matzos, they have some bread it's stored in one
house to allow them to be considered like one רשות reshus to
carry in it, so they would store it in one of the
houses. So you have to, so if it has been stored in
a particular house, you keep it in that house, you don't start
putting it in a different house. We'll see why that will matter.
בור שהיה קרוב לאמה, Bor shehaya karov l'ama, if you had a
well that was near a
what's it called, a
canal, an irrigation canal, מתמלא
ראשון מפני דרכי שלום. mitmaleh rishon mipnei darkhei shalom. So you had
basically the canal which was, you know, it was here or it's
a river or something like this, or the canal, okay, that was
going down near, and here would be the fields, okay, and people
would be irrigated by that water, but sometimes it would dry up.
So what people wanted to do is they would want to store
some of the water, you know, for those types of eventualities. So
you would put a dam here, or you'd put some type of
a blockage, you know, the water would like rise up and you'd
like draw the water and put it in your well and then
it would go down and somebody else could do the same and
they would store water in their wells, you know, for an eventuality
when it was not in that canal. So the question is who
has the right to be the first one to store the water
in case it's scarce, you know, or in case whatever there's a
fight about who gets to store first, so we basically said the
one that's closer to
the outlet of the water, where it starts flowing from, is the
one that has the first right to fill it. מצודות חיה ועופות
ודגים יש בהם משום גזל מפני דרכי שלום. Metzudos chaya v'ofos v'dagim
yesh bahem mishum gezel mipnei darkhei shalom. If you have traps of
birds or wild animals, so I've now trapped this animal, but how
did I take possession of it? I'm not going to until tomorrow
until I go back to my trap, you're going to come upon
it first, you could say, you know, it's not yours, you didn't
physically take possession. Now if the trap actually counts as my כלי
kli and it's in my כלי, kli, then I might be קונה
koneh through a קנין כלי, kinyan kli, but that's not always the
case, right?
So there they basically said in that case we'll treat you as
the owner because of דרכי שלום. darkhei shalom. It's not a case
where it's not just about fighting over like, you know, I mean,
again, some of the cases might, you might have thought that's a
little more תיקון עולם tikkun olam than דרכי שלום, darkhei shalom, but
anyway, you know, it's not just a fight, it's a real question
of like, you have to enable trappers to own the thing that
they trap, right just in order to allow that institution to exist.
Anyway, okay. רבי יוסי אומר גזל גמור. Rabbi Yose omer gezel gamur.
Rabbi Yose says no, no, no, that's real theft. The גמרא Gemara
is going to say he means it doesn't mean דאורייתא d'oraisa theft,
he means rabbinic theft, but he basically says the rabbis didn't just
create a convention that you're allowed to keep it, they actually made
you the owner of it, okay, and it becomes real גזל. gezel.
מציאת חרש שוטה וקטן יש בהם משום גזל מפני דרכי שלום. Metzias
cheresh shoteh v'katan yesh bahem mishum gezel mipnei darkhei shalom. For חרש
שוטה וקטן cheresh shoteh v'katan who are not considered adults, and whatever
they find something they can't really הלכתית halakhically take possession of it,
although we allowed פעוטות pe'utos before, but anyway, but that's a transaction,
anyway, this might be even younger than that age, but so technically
they don't own it, but we say if they find something they
are considered to be the owner because of דרכי שלום. darkhei shalom.
רבי יוסי אומר גזל גמור. Rabbi Yose omer gezel gamur. No, no,
no, it's real גזל. gezel. Again, the גמרא Gemara is going to
say it means rabbinically we made them the real owners, we didn't
just establish a convention.
עני המנקף בראש הזית, Ani hamenakef berosh hazayis, this is similar to
these other cases, it's like the trapper case. You've got a poor
person who went up to the top of an olive tree, maybe
it's a הפקר hefker olive tree, and he's knocking down the olives
from the top of the tree, and you're at the bottom and
you happen to walk by and you say, oh look at all
these olives, and you just take them. Okay? So he doesn't own
them yet, he hasn't done הגבהה, hagbah, he hasn't done a קנין,
kinyan, he just got them all down from the tree. So in
that case מה שתחתיו גזל מפני דרכי שלום. ma shetachtav gezel mipnei
darkhei shalom. It would be considered theft to take what's below because
of דרכי שלום darkhei shalom and רבי יוסי אומר גזל גמור. Rabbi
Yose omer gezel gamur. No, no, no, real theft. Okay exactly what
the difference is we'll see, but anyway we got the idea. Technically
he doesn't own it, but you have to let him own it,
treat it as if he owns it. אין ממיחין ביד עניי עובדי
כוכבים בלקט שכחה ופאה מפני דרכי שלום. Ein memachin beyad aniyei ovdei
kochavim beleket shichcha u'peah mipnei darkhei shalom. This is the דרכי שלום
darkhei shalom that people are more familiar with, but when we get
up to it, it's going to be important to put it in
this context of the דרכי שלום darkhei shalom that we first have
seen. If you have the poor of non-Jews who are coming to
collect to the field and collecting לקט שכחה ופאה leket shichcha u'peah
when the, you know, when it's being left for all the עניים,
aniyim, you don't stop them for the sake of דרכי שלום. darkhei
shalom. Okay, so normally דרכי שלום darkhei shalom is saying like, you
know, so we should get along nice with our non-Jewish neighbors, sometimes
it's translated as very self-serving so that they should be nice to
us, we have to be nice to them, but already we're seeing
that that's not what דרכי שלום darkhei shalom means. דרכי שלום Darkhei
shalom is speaking much more centrally to a value of שלום, shalom,
to a value of doing things in order that it's a type
of a peaceful society, a well-running type of a society, in which
people respect other people's rights and so on. So anyway, or at
least ways in which we don't get into fights. Let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. מנא הני מילי, Mina hani milei, where's
this idea from that we try to do that, that כהנים Kohanim
we give them the first עליה? aliya? to the value of doing
things in order that it's a type of a peaceful society, a
well, well-running type of a society in which people respect other people's
rights and so on. So anyway, or at least ways in which
we don't get into fights. Let's take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. מנא הני מילי? Minanei hani milei? Where's this idea from that
we try to do that, that כהנים Kohanim we give them the
first עליה? Aliyah? אמר רב מתנא דאמר קרא Amar Rav Masna de'amar
kra says, ויכתוב משה את התורה הזאת ויתנה אל הכהנים בני לוי.
Vayichtov Moshe et hatorah hazot vayitnah el hakohanim bnei Levi. So it's
giving the תורה, Torah, so it's about access to the תורה, Torah,
and he gives it to the כהנים Kohanim and then and בני
לוי. Bnei Levi. אטו אנן לא ידעינן דכהנים בני לוי נינהו? Atu
anan lo yadinan de'kohanim bnei Levi ninhu? Of course כהנים Kohanim are
בני לוי. Bnei Levi. אלא כהן ברישא והדר לוי Ela Kohen be'reisha
vehadar Levi to tell you when it comes to the תורה, Torah,
first it's כהנים Kohanim and then it's בני לוי. Bnei Levi. Okay,
that's a nice little אסמכתא. asmachta.
Okay, רבי יצחק נפחא אמר מהכא. Rabbi Yitzchak Napcha amar me'hacha. ונגשו
הכהנים בני לוי Venigshu hakohanim bnei Levi and the כהנים בני לוי
Kohanim bnei Levi drew close. אטו אנן לא ידעינן דכהנים בני לוי
נינהו? Atu anan lo yadinan de'kohanim bnei Levi ninhu? אלא כהן ברישא
והדר לוי Ela Kohen be'reisha vehadar Levi which is fine, but it
wasn't as directly relevant as the example of giving the ספר תורה.
Sefer Torah. רב אשי אמר מהכא. Rav Ashi amar me'hacha. בני עמרם
אהרן ומשה ויבדל אהרן להקדישו קדש קדשים. Bnei Amram Aharon uMoshe vayibadel
Aharon le'hakdisho kodesh kodashim. So there you see Aaron is separated off,
Holy of Holies, and more than Moshe who was a לוי. Levi.
Okay, now so that's saying, so that's just saying that a כהן
Kohen has a higher level of קדושה, kedushah, a higher status. That's
not directly about an עליה Aliyah to the תורה, Torah, which is
then going to raise the question that the גמרא Gemara is going
to turn to. רבי חייא בר אבא מהכא. Rabbi Chiya bar Abba
me'hacha. וקדשתו, Vekidashto, the פסוק pasuk by כהנים, Kohanim, you should sanctify
him לכל דבר שבקדושה, lekhol davar shebikdusha, anything relating to a matter
of sanctity or showing status. לפתוח ראשון, Liftoach rishon, that they get
to open first, like you know, to give the first speech or
the first
דרשה. drashah. ולברך ראשון Ulvarekh rishon to lead ברכת המזון. Birkat Hamazon.
וליטול מנה יפה בראשון, Ulitol manah yafah be'rishon, or if you're like,
I don't know, like handing out, you know, they're picking around the
platter of chicken, he gets the first choice. Okay, so so it's
not talking about financial matters of like dividing up an estate or
something like that, that's already a different story. But anyway, but when
it's just a matter of כבוד. kavod. Okay. So that's where you
get it from. Of course, now it's no longer דרכי שלום, darchei
shalom, right? Now it's not just an אסמכתא, asmachta, now it's like
wait a minute, so there's a real דאורייתא de'oraisa concept of giving
him these honors. אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף. Amar leh Abaye le'Rav
Yosef. So Abaye said to Rav Yosef, מפני דרכי שלום, דאורייתא? Mipnei
darchei shalom, de'oraisa? So it's not just דרכי שלום, darchei shalom, it's
דאורייתא. de'oraisa. We're supposed to in cases of status
and showing honor, we're supposed to afford him that status. So that
translates to קריאת התורה. krias hatorah. Even if the institution of קריאת
התורה krias hatorah is rabbinic, the idea of when you have proper
settings you show him this honor, that's a דאורייתא de'oraisa idea. So
let's see what Rav Yosef said back. אמר ליה, Amar leh, דאורייתא
ומפני דרכי שלום. De'oraisa u'mipnei darchei shalom. Yes, it's דאורייתא de'oraisa and
the תורה Torah is telling us to do it מפני דרכי שלום.
mipnei darchei shalom. Now that's funny because that's not why the תורה
Torah is telling us to do it. The תורה Torah is telling
us to do it because the תורה Torah is saying they're of
a higher status and you have to acknowledge that. That's not a
דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. That's acknowledging what it means to be of
a higher קדושה kedushah and the roles that they play and the
importance that that has in society. Anyway, somehow you could fit that
in maybe to דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. Anyway, Abaye doesn't like this.
Abaye says, כל התורה כולה נמי מפני דרכי שלום. Kol hatorah kullah
nami mipnei darchei shalom. So let's just say that every דאורייתא de'oraisa
is דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. Everything in the תורה Torah is ultimately
rooted in a concept of שלום. shalom. This is very powerful statement.
דכתיב דרכיה דרכי נועם וכל נתיבותיה שלום. De'chtiv deracheha darchei noam vekhol
netivoteha shalom.
Everything is a way of peace. Okay, we're going to come back
to that פסוק pasuk later when we get to the issue about
relations with non-Jews and דרכי שלום. darchei shalom. רמב"ם Rambam uses that
פסוק pasuk in that discussion. So keep that in mind. But anyway,
he's saying you can't say this is דרכי שלום darchei shalom because
it's from the תורה. Torah. Then you know then you could use
that phrase to explain anything that's in the תורה. Torah. We want
to believe it's all based on a principle of שלום. shalom. אלא
אמר אביי לכי דמר. Ela amar Abaye lechi d'mar. Like what מר
Mar the master teaches, which is,
Rashi says it's I forget who the מר Mar is here.
Anyway, where's רש"י? Rashi?
Oh, רבה בר נחמני. Rabbah bar Nachmani. Or like it's רבה's Rabbah
teaching. דתניא, De'tanya, it was taught in a ברייתא. beraisa. שנים ממתינים
זה לזה בקערה. Shnayim mamtinim zeh lazeh be'kearah. If two if if
you're eating lunch with somebody and the other guy is like kind
of coming back washing his hands or whatever he's doing, he's coming
late to the table, you wait for him to get to the
table before you start digging in, you know, digging into the food
and taking the chicken off the platter. שלשה אין ממתינים. Shloshah ein
mamtinim. If there are three people though, you don't wait and one
guy's taking his time, so you don't have to wait for him.
Okay, so המוציא, Hamotzi, so these are like laws of סעודה. seudah.
המוציא הוא פושט ידו תחילה. Hamotzi hu poshet yado techilah. The one
who broke the bread, he's the one that gets to first dip
his bread into the the dips in the middle of the table.
ואם בא לחלוק כבוד לרבו או למי שגדול ממנו הרשות בידו. Ve'im
ba lachalok kavod lerabbo o lemi shegadol mimmenu hareshut beyado. But if
you want to give honor, you know, even though you're the one
who broke the bread, to your
master or to somebody who's of greater status,
you're allowed to.
ואמר מר Ve'amar Mar and רבה Rabbah explained this הלכה, halakhah, לא
שנו אלא בסעודה. Lo shanu ela biseudah. The idea that you're allowed
to be מוחל mochel on your כבוד kavod if you're the גדול
הבית, gadol habayis, if you're the person who broke the bread, that's
at a meal, that's at a home-based type of thing. אבל בבית
הכנסת לא דאתו לאינצויי. Aval beveit haknesset lo de'atu le'intzuyei. But not
in שול shul because it'll lead to fights. Which means what? Let's
see the way רש"י Rashi explains it is the answer is the
following. You know what? You're right. Giving the כהן Kohen the first
עליה, Aliyah, that's a דאורייתא de'oraisa because of וקדשתו. ve'kidashto. But let's
say the כהן Kohen wants to say I'm מוחל, mochel, I know
this is my honor, but I want to give it to my
good friend first, I'm מוחל, mochel, I want him to go before
me, he's a big תלמיד חכם, talmid chakham, he's my רבי, Rebbe,
and so on. So that's where the Rabbis come in and say
we're not going to let you do that. We're not going to
let you be מוחל mochel on your כבוד. kavod. Why? Because what
happen if we let you be מוחל mochel on your כבוד? kavod?
Then everybody's going to want, well, so why didn't you let me
go, why didn't you give me the, it leads to the דרכי
שלום Darchei Shalom problems once, yes, so showing the honor is דאורייתא,
d'Oraisa, but making sure that it keeps that way, and the כהנים
Kohanim don't start being מוחל mochel on their כבוד, kavod, which then
could just lead to fights, that's what is, that's the rabbinic. Just
read, let me just, I guess that's, let's just read one more
line. אמר רב מתנא, Amar Rav Mattana, הא דאמרינן Ha d'amrinan בבית
הכנסת B'veit HaKnesset לא, lo, that a כהן Kohen can't be מוחל
mochel on his כבוד kavod in the שול, shul, לא אמרן lo
amran אלא ela בשבתות b'Shabbatos וימים טובים. v'Yamim Tovim. That's only on
שבת Shabbos and יום טוב, Yom Tov, דשכיחי d'sh'chichi רבים, rabim, that
there's a big crowd in שול, shul, see nothing ever changes. אבל
Aval בשני b'sheni וחמישי, v'chamishi, on Mondays and Thursdays, לא, lo, there's
not a big crowd so he could be מוחל mochel on his
כבוד, kavod, it's not a big deal. Okay, so, you know what,
let's not start this. We'll pick up with this point tomorrow. Okay,
so more on כהנים Kohanim and עליות aliyos and דרכי שלום Darchei
Shalom tomorrow.